Finding Aid for Kermit Krueger papers, Kermit Krueger papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Kermit Krueger papers ca. 1963-1965
Krueger, Kermit
1 linear foot
2014029 Aa 2
Papers of Kermit Krueger, a University of Michigan alumnus who served as a Peace Corps Volunteer in Thailand from 1963 to 1965 and subsequently published two books of Thai folk stories he had collected during his time in the Peace Corps. The collection reflects Krueger's experiences living in a Thai village, teaching English in Thailand, traveling the country, and visiting other Asian countries while abroad.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Kermit Krueger (donor no. 10961 ) in July 2013.
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open without restriction..
In 1963 a recent graduate of the University of Michigan, Kermit Krueger, enrolled as a Peace Corps volunteer after having been inspired by a speech given by John F. Kennedy in 1960 on the steps of the Michigan Union in Ann Arbor, Michigan. Krueger was assigned to teach English at the Teacher's Training College in Mahasarakham, Thailand. While living in Thailand, Krueger documented his experiences with village life in Mahasarakham, Buddhist practices and rituals, and teaching English to the college students.
In an effort to help integrate English into his students' vocabularies, Krueger assigned each of them to write a folk story in English that was from or about their places of origin in Thailand. Krueger helped his students to edit and improve the English stories. He then created a compilation of the stories to be used as a student reader for teaching English at the Teacher's Training College.
After Krueger returned to the United States approximately half of the Thai stories were compiled and published by the World Publishing Company in the book The Serpent Prince (1969). Shortly following the publication of The Serpent Prince a single Thai story Krueger had recorded, The Gold Swans of Chaiyapum (1969) was also published by the World Publishing Company.
The papers of Kermit Krueger document the experiences of a young Peace Corps volunteer living and exploring culture in Asian villages and cities in the early 1960s. This collection contains documents and artifacts created and collected by Krueger during his service in the Peace Corps from 1963 to 1965 as well as documents created after his return to the United States that reflect on his time in Thailand. The collection is organized into four series: Stories from Thailand, Visual Materials, Correspondence, and Travel Materials.
Subjects:
East Asia--Description and travel.; Krueger, Kermit.; Maha Sarakham (Thailand: Province); Peace Corps (U.S.); Southeast Asia--Description and travel.; Tales--Thailand.; Villages--Thailand.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
East Asia--Description and travel.; Krueger, Kermit.; Maha Sarakham (Thailand: Province); Peace Corps (U.S.); Southeast Asia--Description and travel.; Villages--Thailand.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Slides (photographs).
- Stories from Thailand
  The series Stories from Thailand (1963-1965) contains handwritten and printed drafts of Thai folk stories by Krueger's students at the Teacher's Training College, some are edited and annotated by Krueger. The series also includes Krueger's hand written compilations of Thai stories and notes on Thai culture that he gathered from his students and his printed compilations of Thai stories in the form of student readers and manuscripts, including:Stories from the North East, Thai Folk Tales and Stories, The Plain of the Trader Who Cried: Stories from North East Thailand, and A Day at the Races. Most of the manuscripts include written introductions.
  - Student Drafts, 1963-1965 (Box 1)
  - Story Compilations, undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
    (includes Krueger's original manuscripts)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials (ca.1963-1965) series contains images capturing Krueger's experiences while in the Peace Corps. The series includes Krueger's photographs of the people and places at the Teacher's Training College in Mahasarakham, Thailand, and photographs depicting daily life and practices in Thai villages. The other visual materials in the series are Krueger's photographic slides depicting: Peace Corps training in Elkhorn, Wisconsin, life at the Teacher's Training College, and his travels throughout Thailand, China, Japan, Vietnam, and other Asian cities and villages. Finally, the series includes notes written by Krueger describing the content of the slides. These notes were originally found in a binder accompanying the slides. The visual materials are arranged by location and events.
  - Photographs, ca. 1963-1965, 2 envelopes (Box 1)
  - Photographic Slides, ca. 1963-1965, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Notes on Slides, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence (1963-1965) series primarily contains airmail letters written from Krueger to his parents with several letters he wrote to his sister and grandparents, all sent during his time in the Peace Corps from September 1963 to August 1965. The series also contains postcards sent from Kermit Krueger to his family members while he was living in Thailand. The Correspondence series is arranged chronologically.
  - September-December, 1963 (Box 1)
  - January-March, 1964 (Box 1)
  - April-June, 1964 (Box 1)
  - July-September, 1964 (Box 1)
  - October-December, 1964 (Box 1)
  - January-March, 1965 (Box 1)
  - April-August, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Postcards, ca. 1963-1965 (Box 1)
- Travel Materials
  The Travel Materials (1963-1965) series contains Thai artifacts collected by Krueger during his time there, including a map of Thailand and a Thai 45 rpm single vinyl record. The series also contains travel documents of Krueger's that were used for identification in international travel and service in the Peace Corps.
  - Thai Artifacts, ca. 1963-1965 (Box 1)
  - Travel and Peace Corps Documents, 1963-1965 (Box 1)